Achuta Kadambi

Associate Professor Electrical Engineering and Computer Science (EECS) University of California, Los Angeles

Email: achuta@ucla.edu

Lab Website: http://visual.ee.ucla.edu

Bio: Achuta Kadambi (PhD, MIT '18) is an Associate Professor at UCLA in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science. He leads a research group at the intersection of computer vision, physics, computational imaging, AI, and medical devices. He is the recipient of early career awards including from NSF (CAREER), DARPA (YFA), ARO (YIP), IEEE (HKN under 35 award), and Forbes (30 under 30). He has co-founded two California companies to commercialize research technologies. One, Akasha Imaging, was acquired by Alphabet for its robot automation technology. The other is Vayu Robotics, working on perception-driven robot navigation. Kadambi has filed over 70 patents, 30+ of which have been issued to date.

Education

 $\begin{array}{ccc} \text{PhD} & \text{MIT}^1 & 2018 \\ \text{MS} & \text{Yale} & 2012 \\ \text{BS} & \text{Berkeley} & 2011 \\ \end{array}$

¹ Interdepartmental Doctoral Degree Program between the MIT Media Lab and MIT EECS

Academic Appointments

Assoc. Prof.	UCLA (Elec. Engr. & Comp Sci.)	2024-
Asst. Prof.	UCLA (Comp. Sci.)	2021-2024
Asst. Prof.	UCLA (Elec. & Comp. Engr.)	2018-2024

Start-up Companies Founded

Co-founder	Akasha Imaging (acquired by Alphabet)	2018-2022
Co-founder	Vayu (backed by Khosla Ventures)	2022-pres

Awards

2024 2022 2022 2021 2021 2021 2020 2020	Best Paper Award, ICCP Lemelson-MIT Student Prize Rahamimoff Award, US-Israel Science Foundation Best Papers Special Issue Selection, ICCV Best Presentation Award, CVPR VIEW World Changing Idea, Scientific American Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship	UCLA UCLA UCLA UCLA UCLA UCLA UCLA UCLA
2014	Qualcomm Innovation Fellowship	MIT
2013	Draper Fellowship	MIT

Awards won by UCLA Students

2023	Distinguished Master's Thesis Award, ECE Department (Adnan Armouti)
2022	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship GRFP, Winner (Ellin Zhao)
2022	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship GRFP, Hon. Mention (Sasha Vilesov)
2021	Cisco PhD Fellowship (Pradyumna Chari)
2020	Guru Krupa Graduate Fellowship, UCLA (Chinmay Talegaonkar)
2019	Best Undergrad Demo, Annual Research Review (A Padhye, A Tilaye, et al)
2019	Best Poster, runner up. SoCal Machine Learning Day (Yunhao Ba)

Invited Talks

- 2024 Invited Speaker, DARPA Triage Challenge (DTC) Meeting
- 2024 **Keynote**, CVPR 2024, UG2 Workshop (Seattle WA)
- 2024 Invited Speaker, Army Research Lab (Playa Vista CA)
- 2023 Lecturer, SIGGRAPH 2023, Course on Polarization (Los Angeles CA)
- 2023 Lecturer, CVPR 2023, Tutorial on Polarization (Vancouver Canada)
- 2023 Invited Speaker, SID Display Conference (Los Angeles CA)
- 2023 UC Davis, Bioengineering Seminar (Davis, CA)
- 2022 **Keynote**, CVPR UG2 Workshop (New Orleans, LA)
- 2022 **Keynote**, CVPR CVPM Workshop (New Orleans, LA)
- 2022 University of Maryland, Computer Science (Wash. DC)
- 2022 CMU Bioengineering Department Seminar (Pittsburgh, PA)
- 2022 Optical Sensors and Sensing Congress (Vancouver, CA)
- 2021 MIT AeroAstro Department (Cambridge, MA)
- 2021 Boston University Electrical Engineering Department (Boston, MA)
- 2021 EPFL, Lausanne Switzerland (Rescheduled COVID)
- 2021 UCLA Medical School Grand Rounds, Los Angeles CA (Los Angeles, CA)
- 2021 Snap Inc. (Virtual)
- 2021 Cornell AI in Medicine Seminar (Virtual)
- 2021 ETH Zurich Computer Vision Seminar (Zurich, Switzerland)
- 2021 Amazon + UCLA Science Hub Kickoff Event (Los Angeles, CA)
- 2021 Pixel Cafe at UCSD (Virtual)
- 2021 UC Berkeley Bioengineering, Guest Lecturer for Medical Devices (Virtual)
- 2021 Black in Neuro Panel, Imperial College London (Virtual)
- 2021 Army Research Lab A2I2 Summit (Virtual)
- 2021 ICCV GigaVision Workshop (Virtual)
- 2021 CLEO Panel on AI and Photonics (Virtual)
- 2021 Army Research Lab Workshop on Synthetic Data (Virtual)
- 2020 SPIE Workshop on Computational Imaging (Virtual)
- 2020 Army Research Lab, Adelphi MD
- 2020 CVPR Visual Physics, Seattle WA
- 2019 DARPA/MEC workshop on AI, San Jose CA
- 2019 Stanford EE Department, Stanford CA
- 2019 MIT Media Lab, Cambridge MA
- 2019 Lemelson-MIT Eurekafest, Cambridge MA
- 2019 Computational Light Transport Summit, Banff Canada
- 2019 Indian Institute of Science, EE Department, Bangalore India
- 2019 Machine Learning Summer School, Bangalore India
- 2019 Honeywell Technology Symposium, Phoenix AZ
- 2019 Annual Research Review, UCLA, Los Angeles CA
- 2018 University of California, Los Angeles CA
- 2018 Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh PA
- 2018 MIT CSAIL, Cambridge MA
- 2017 University of Tokyo, Tokyo JP
- 2017 Cymer Semiconductor Equipment, San Diego CA
- 2017 Computer Vision and Information Processing Society of Japan, Nagoya JP
- 2016 Honeywell Technology Symposium, Phoenix AZ
- 2016 Columbia CS, New York City, NY
- 2016 Cornell Tech, CS New York City, NY

- 2016 Mitsubishi Electric Research Lab (MERL), Boston MA
- 2016 University of Pennsylvania GRASP Lab, Philadelphia PA
- 2016 Princeton CS, Princeton, New Jersey
- 2016 Weizmann Institute of Science, Rehovat Israel
- 2016 Technion CS Department, Haifa Israel
- 2016 Mass General Hospital (MGH), Boston MA
- 2016 OSA Invited Talk, Heidelberg Germany
- 2016 Analog Devices, Cambridge MA
- 2015 Computational Imaging Summit, Daghstuhl Germany
- 2015 Microsoft Research, Redmond WA
- 2014 Qualcomm Research, San Diego CA
- 2014 Technion, Haifa Israel
- 2014 Microsoft iToF Workshop, Ein Gadi Israel
- 2014 IIT-Bombay, Bombay India
- 2013 Nokia Research, Bangalore India

Professional Service

Industry Chair, ICCP 2020, ICCP 2022, ICCP 2023

Invited Guest Editor, Applied Sciences, Special Issue, Computational Photography

Program chair, CVPR CCD 2021

Program chair, CVPR CCD 2020

Program chair, Industry relations, ICCP 2020

Program committee, Pacific Graphics 2019

Program committee, CVPR 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021

Program committee, ICCP 2018, 2019, 2020, 2021, 2022, 2023

Program committee, ICCV PBDL Workshop 2017

Reviewer, SIGGRAPH

Reviewer, SIGGRAPH Asia

Reviewer, ICCV

Reviewer, CVPR

Reviewer, ECCV

Reviewer, ICCP

Reviewer, IEEE Trans Comp Imaging (TCI)

Reviewer, Various OSA journals

University Service, UCLA ECE TA Awards Committee 2023

University Service, UCLA, MS admissions committee

University Service, UCLA, PhD thesis award committee

University Service, MIT, undergrad admissions committee

University Service, Lemelson-MIT student prize selection committee

IEEE. ACM. and OSA member

Co-instructor, "Polarization-based Visual Computing", SIGGRAPH 2023

Co-instructor, "Polarization-Based Computer Vision", CVPR 2023

Textbook

TB.1 A. Bhandari, **A. Kadambi**, R. Raskar, *Computational Imaging (450 pages).* **MIT Press**, 2022 (E-PDF at imagingtext.github.io)

Papers Published

https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=UMzWJikAAAAJ&hl=en&oi=ao

- P.33 Zhou, S., Chang, H., Jiang, S., Fan, Z., Zhu, Z., Xu, D., Chari, P., You, S., Wang, Z. and **Kadambi, A.** Feature 3dgs: Supercharging 3d gaussian splatting to enable distilled feature fields. **CVPR 2024 (Highlight Paper)**
- P.32 R. Upadhyay, H. Zhang, Y. Ba, E. Yang, B. Gella, S. Jiang, A. Wong, and A. Kadambi. Enhancing Diffusion Models with 3D Perspective Geometry Constraints. ACM SIGGRAPH Asia 2023 (journal)
- P.31 Z. Wang, S. Zhou, J. Park, D. Paschalidou, S. You, G. Wetzstein, L. Guibas, and A. Kadambi. *ALTO: Alternating Latent Topologies for Implicit 3D Reconstruction*. **CVPR 2023**
- P.30 H. Zhang, Y. Ba, E. Yang, V. Mehra, B. Gella, A. Suzuki, A. Pfahnl, C. Chandrappa, A. Wong, and **A. Kadambi.** *WeatherStream: Light Transport Automation of Single Image Deweathering.* **CVPR 2023**
- P.29 A. Singh, Y. Ba, A. Sarker, H. Zhang, **A. Kadambi,** S. Soatto, M. Srivastava, A. Wong. *Depth Estimation from Camera Image and mmWave Radar Point Cloud.* **CVPR 2023**
- P.28 H. Peters, Y. Ba, and **A. Kadambi**. *pCON: Polarimetric Coordinate Networks for Neural Scene Representations*. **CVPR 2023**
- P.27 A. Kadambi, C. de Melo, C. Hsieh, M. Srivastava, S. Soatto. *Incorporating physics into data-driven computer vision*. **Nature Machine Intelligence 2023.** https://doi.org/10.1038/s42256-023-00662-0
- P.26 P. Chari, Y. Ba, S. Zhou, C. Talegaonkar, S. Athreya, and **A. Kadambi.** "On Learning Mechanical Laws of Motion From Video Using Neural Networks." **IEEE Access 11 (2023): 30129-30145.**
- P.25 P. Chari, Y. Ba, S. Athreya, and **A. Kadambi**. *MIME: Minority Inclusion for Majority Group Enhancement of AI Performance*. **ECCV 2022**
- P.24 Y. Ba, H. Zhang, E. Yang, A. Suzuki, A. Pfahnl, C. Chandrappa, C. De Melo, S. You, S. Soatto, A. Wong, and **A. Kadambi.** *Not Just Streaks: Towards Ground Truth for Single Image Deraining.* **ECCV 2022**
- P.23 Y. Ba*, Z. Wang*, D. Karinca, O. Bozkurt, and **A. Kadambi**. *Style Transfer*

- with Bio-realistic Appearance Manipulation for Skin-tone Inclusive Plethysmography ICCP 2022
- P.22 A. Vilesov*, P. Chari*, A. Armouti*, A. B. Harish, K. Kulkarni, A. Deoghare, L. Jalilian, and **A. Kadambi**. *Blending Camera and 77 GHz Radar Sensing for Equitable, Robust Plethysmography*. **SIGGRAPH 2022** (journal)
- P.21 Z. Wang, Y. Ba, P. Chari, O. Bozkurt, G. Brown, P. Patwa, N. Vaddi, L. Jalilian, and **A. Kadambi,** Synthetic *Generation of Face Videos with Plethysmograph Physiology.* **CVPR 2022**
- P.20 S. Pei, P. Chari, X. Wang, X. Yang, **A. Kadambi**, and Y. Zhang. *ForceSight: Non-Contact Force Sensing with Laser Speckle Imaging.* **UIST 2022**
- P.19 B. Jalali, Y. Zhou, A. Kadambi, and V. Roychowdhury. *Physics-Al Symbiosis*. **ML Science and Technology 2022**
- P.18 **A. Kadambi**, *Achieving Fairness in Medical Devices*. **Science** 2021 no. 372.6537
- P.17 A. Kalra, B. Brown, G Stoppi, R. Agrawal, and **A. Kadambi**. *Towards Rotation Invariance in Object Detection*. **ICCV 2021**.
- P.16 **A. Kadambi** and A. Madni, *Artificial Intelligence: From Ancient Greeks to Self-Driving Cars and Beyond*, **Nat'l Academy of Engineering Bridge 2021**
- P.15 Y. Ba, A. Gilbert, F. Wang, J. Yang, R. Chen, Y. Wang, B. Shi and A. Kadambi. Deep Shape from Polarization. ECCV 2020.
- P.14 K. Tanaka, Y. Mukaigawa, and **A. Kadambi.** *Polarized Non-line-of-sight Imaging.* **CVPR 2020**
- P.13 A. Kalra, V. Taamazyan, S. Rao, K. Venkataraman, R Raskar, and **A. Kadambi.** *Deep Polarization Cues for Transparent Object Segmentation.* **CVPR 2020 (Oral)**
- P.12 K. Tanaka, N. Ikeya, T. Takatani, H. Kubo, T. Funatomi, V. Ravi, **A. Kadambi**, and Y. Mukaigawa. *Time-resolved Far Infrared Light Transport Decomposition for Thermal Photometric Stereo*. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (**TPAMI**), **2020**
- P.11 T. Maeda, Y. Wang, R. Raskar, and A. Kadambi. Thermal Non-line-of-sight Imaging. IEEE ICCP 2019
- P.10 T. Maeda, **A. Kadambi**, Y. Schechner, and R. Raskar. *Dynamic heterodyne interferometry*. IEEE **ICCP 2018 (Best Paper Award)**
- P.9 **A. Kadambi** and R. Raskar. *Rethinking Machine Vision Time of Flight with GHz Heterodyning.* IEEE **Access 2017**

- P.8 **A. Kadambi**, V. Taamazyan, B. Shi, and R. Raskar. *Depth sensing using geometrically constrained polarization normals*. In **IJCV 2017** (**Best Papers Issue**)
- P.7 **A. Kadambi**, J. Schiel, and R. Raskar. *Macroscopic Interferometry:*Rethinking Depth Estimation with Frequency-Domain Time of Flight. IEEE
 CVPR 2016 (Oral, 3% acceptance rate).
- P.6 **A. Kadambi**, H. Zhao, B. Shi, and R. Raskar. *Occluded Imaging with Time of Flight Sensors*. In ACM Transactions on Graphics (pres **SIGGRAPH 2016**)
- P.5 **A. Kadambi,** V. Taamazyan, B. Shi, and R. Raskar. *Polarized 3D: enhanced 3D sensing fusing depth and polarization cues.* **ICCV 2015 (Oral)**
- P.4 N. Naik, **A. Kadambi**, C. Rhemann, S. Izadi, R. Raskar and S. Kang. *A light transport model for mitigating multipath interference in ToF sensors*. In **CVPR 2015**.
- P.3 A. Bhandari, **A. Kadambi**, R. Whyte, C. Barsi, M. Feigin, A. Dorrington, and R. Raskar. *Resolving multi-path interference in time-of-flight imaging via modulation frequency diversity and sparse regularization*. **Optics Letters**, **2014**
- P.2 **A. Kadambi**, A. Bhandari, R. Whyte, A. Dorrington and R. Raskar. *Demultiplexing Illumination via low-cost sensing and nanosecond coding.* **ICCP 2014**.
- P.1 **A. Kadambi**, R. Whyte, A. Bhandari, L. Streeter, C. Barsi, A. Dorrington, and R. Raskar. *Coded time of flight cameras: sparse deconvolution to address multipath interference and recover time profiles.* ACM Transactions on Graphics (pres **SIGGRAPH Asia 2013**).

US Patents

- US.31 Systems and methods for high dynamic range image reconstruction. **US Patent #12,020,455** (publication date: 2024-06-25)
- US.30 Systems and methods for pose detection and measurement. **US Patent** #12,008,796 (publication date: 2024-06-11)
- US.29 *In-hand pose refinement for pick and place automation.* **US Patent #11,986,955** (publication date: 2024-05-21)
- US.28 Systems and methods for augmentation of sensor systems and imaging systems with polarization (continuation) **US Patent #11,982,775** (publication date: 2024-05-14)

- US.27 *Multi-aperture polarization optical systems using beam splitters* **US Patent #11,953,700** (publication date: 2024-04-09)
- US.26 Systems and methods for six-degree of freedom pose estimation of deformable objects **US Patent #11,954,886** (publication date: 2024-04-09)
- US.25 Systems and methods for transparent object segmentation using polarization cues (continuation) **US Patent #11,842,495** (publication date: 2023-12-12)
- US.24 Systems and methods for synthesizing data for training statistical models on different imaging modalities including polarized images. **US Patent** #11,797,863 (publication date: 2023-10-24)
- US.23 Systems and methods for surface modeling using polarization cues (continuation). **US Patent #11,699,273** (publication date: 2023-07-11)
- US.22 Systems and methods for high dynamic range imaging using crossed polarizers. **US Patent #11,689,813**
- US.21 Systems and methods for camera exposure control. US Patent #11,683,594
- US.20 Systems and methods for augmentation of sensor systems and imaging systems with polarization. **US Patent #11,525,906**
- US.19 Systems and methods for transparent object segmentation using polarization cues. **US Patent #11,302,012**
- US.18 Systems and methods for pose detection and measurement **US Patent** #11,295,475
- US.17 Systems and methods for camera exposure control. US Patent #11,290,658
- US.16 Systems and methods for surface modeling using polarization cues. **US #Patent 11,270,110**
- US.15 Systems and methods for characterizing object pose detection and measurement systems. **US Patent #11,195,303**
- US.14 Methods and apparatus for gigahertz time-of-flight imaging. **US Patent** #11,181,623
- US.13 Depth maps with polarization cues. US Patent #10,557,705
- US.12 X-ray imaging from temporal measurements. US Patent #10,527,562
- US.11 Time-of-flight sensor. US Patent #10,488,520

US.10	Fluorescent lifetime with periodically modulated light. US Patent #10,337,993
US.9	Depth maps with polarization cues. US Patent #10,260,866
US.8	Methods and apparatus for time-of-flight imaging. US Patent #10,191,154
US.7	Fluorescence lifetime imaging with pulsed light. US Patent #10,190,983
US.6	Methods and apparatus for virtual sensor array. US Patent #9,897,699
US.5	Intensity-based depth sensing system and method. US Patent #9,897,698
US.4	Methods and apparatus for coded time-of-flight camera. US Patent #9,778,363
US.3	Depth sensing using optical pulses and fixed coded aperture. US Patent #9,638,801
US.2	Methods and apparatus for demultiplexing illumination. US Patent #9,451,141

US.1 Methods and apparatus for multi-frequency camera. **US Patent #9,405,008**